Guide to the George Kalinsky Photographs of Muhammad Ali 1965–1999 PR 325
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
George Kalinsky photographs of Muhammad Ali
1965–1999
PR 325
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
6.5 Linear feet (45 prints of 44 images in 3 oversize boxes)
45 mostly black-and-white photographs documenting the career of boxer Muhammad Ali (1942-2016). The images formed the New-York Historical Society exhibition “I Am King of the World”: Photographs of Muhammad Ali by George Kalinsky, December 2016 - March 2017.
Kalinsky, George, (b. 1936)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from George Kalinsky, 2016-2017.
Arrangement
The photographs are filed in numerical order. They are matted and numbered on the backs of their mounts to match their exhibition checklist order. A copy of this checklist is filed in Box 1. All images are black-and-white except for those marked [color print].
Biographical Note
Sports and entertainment photographer George Kalinsky (b. 1936, Hempstead, N.Y.) landed the job of official photographer for Madison Square Garden in 1966, a year after bluffing his way into Muhammad Ali's workout session there. The two men became fast friends, and Kalinsky captured on film the seminal events of "the great one's" career until Ali's death in 2016.
Kalinsky's award-winning work (he was named PMDA International Photographer of the Year in 2001) has been shown throughout the world, and is found in the permanent collections of the Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame, the National Baseball Hall of Fame, the Jewish Museum of New York, Cornell University, and the New-York Historical Society.
For more information visit the photographer's website: https://georgekalinsky.com/
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Scope and Contents
The 41 prints in this collection formed a New-York Historical Society exhibition curated by Dr. Marilyn S. Kushner titled “I Am King of the World”: Photographs of Muhammad Ali by George Kalinsky. It ran concurrently with Muhammad Ali, LeRoy Neiman, and the Art of Boxing, from December 2016 through March 2017. Kalinsky's images document Ali's career between 1965 and 1999.
Highlights include:
1965: working out at the 5th Street Gym, Miami; speaking to sportscaster Howard Cosell
1967: training at Madison Square Garden; his bout vs. Zora Folley
1971: his rivalry with basketball great Wilt Chamberlain; his bout vs. Joe Frazier, called the "Fight of the Century"
1972: training at Deer Lake, Pennsylvania for his bout vs. Floyd Patterson
1976: promoting his fight with Ken Norton at Yankee Stadium; signing autographs at the Concord Resort Hotel in the Catskills
1977: his bout vs. Earnie Shavers
1984: sitting ringside at WrestleMania
1999: receiving Sports Illustrated's Sportsman of the Century award
Ali, Muhammad, 1942-2016 -- Pictorial works; Chamberlain, Wilt, 1936-1999; Cosell, Howard, 1918-1995.; Folley, Zora, 1931-1972; Frazier, Joe, 1944-2011; Norton, Ken, 1943-2013; Patterson, Floyd.; Shavers, Earnie, 1944-; Boxers (Sports) -- United States.; Boxing -- United States.; Boxing--Pictorial works.
- Muhammad Ali working out at Madison Square Garden, 1967 (Box 1, Item 1)
- Muhammad Ali working out at his training facility in Deer Lake, Pennsylvania, 1972 (Box 1, Item 2)
- Muhammad Ali working out at 5th St. Gym, Miami, 1965 (Box 1, Item 3)
- Sportscaster Howard Cosell interviewing Ali in Miami, 1965 (Box 1, Item 4)
- Muhammad Ali vs Zora Folley fight [color print], 1967 (Box 1, Item 5)
- Muhammad Ali after the Folley fight [color print], 1967 (Box 1, Item 6)
- Joe Frazier and Muhammad Ali, 1971 (Box 1, Item 7)
- Joe Frazier and Muhammad Ali [color print], 1971 (Box 1, Item 8)
- Muhammad Ali training at Joe Frazier’s gym [color print], 1971 (Box 1, Item 9)
- Outside Joe Frazier’s gym [color print], 1971 (Box 1, Item 10)
- Joe Frazier and Muhammad Ali at a press conference, 1973 (Box 1, Item 11)
- Muhammad Ali vs Joe Frazier, 1971 [color print] (Box 1, Item 12)
- Muhammad Ali vs Joe Frazier [color print], 1971 (Box 1, Item 13)
- Muhammad Ali vs Joe Frazier [color print], 1971 (Box 1, Item 14)
- Muhammad Ali vs Floyd Patterson, 1972 (Box 2, Item 15)
- Floyd Patterson and Muhammad Ali at Deer Lake, Ali’s training camp in Pennsylvania, 1972 (Box 2, Item 16)
- Muhammad Ali promoting his fight with Ken Norton at Yankee Stadium, 1976 (Box 2, Item 17)
- Muhammad Ali training at the Concord Resort Hotel, 1976 (Box 2, Item 18)
- Muhammad Ali training at the 5th St. Gym [Miami], 1965 (Box 2, Item 19)
- Muhammad Ali vs Earnie Shavers [color print], 1977 (Box 2, Item 20)
- Muhammad Ali and Wilt Chamberlain, early 1970s (Box 2, Item 21)
- Muhammad Ali with Floyd Patterson, 1972 (Box 2, Item 22)
- Muhammad Ali at a newsstand in New York City, 1967 (Box 2, Item 23)
- Muhammad Ali at his training facility in Deer Lake, Pennsylvania, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Item 24)
- Muhammad Ali driving a busload of reporters, early 1970s (Box 2, Item 25)
- Muhammad Ali resting at his training facility in Deer Lake, Pennsylvania, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Item 26)
- Muhammad Ali sleeping after a workout, 1967 (Box 2, Item 27)
- Muhammad Ali resting during a break in workouts, 1974 (Box 2, Item 28)
- Muhammad Ali after a training run through Miami, 1970 (Box 3, Item 29)
- Muhammad Ali working out at 5th St. Gym, Miami, 1965 (Box 3, Item 30)
- Muhammad Ali during a workout break at Madison Square Garden, 1967 (Box 3, Item 31)
- Muhammad Ali and reporters, 1967 (Box 3, Item 32)
- Muhammad Ali and the press [color print], 1976 (Box 3, Item 33)
- Muhammad Ali in Miami, 1974 (Box 3, Item 34)
- Muhammad Ali signing autographs at the Concord Resort Hotel in the Catskills, 1976 (Box 3, Item 35)
- Muhammad Ali training at Madison Square Garden, 1967 (Box 3, Item 36)
- Sports Illustrated athletes of the century [color print], 1999 (Box 3, Item 37)
- Muhammad Ali sits ringside at WrestleMania [color print], 1984 (Box 3, Item 38)
- Muhammad Ali receiving his award as the Sports Illustrated Sportsman of the Century [color print], 1999 (Box 3, Item 39)
- Joe Frazier with Muhammad Ali [color print], 1999 (Box 3, Item 40)
- Muhammad Ali at Deer Lake, Pennsylvania, training camp [near boulder painted with “Rocky Graziano”] (2 copies), 1974-1976 (Box 3, Item 41-42)
- Dizzy Gillespie and Muhammad Ali, 1976 (Box 3, Item 43)
- Muhammad Ali vs Oscar Bonavena [color print], 1970 (Box 3, Item 44)
- Muhammad Ali with a coloring book of military officers, 1967 (Box 3, Item 45)